ערב טוב, Erev tov, also want to welcome, I believe this week
we're being followed by the בית שלום Beth Shalom congregation in
Potomac, Rabbi Nissan Antine's שול. shul. Hello Maryland. So I welcome them.
Okay, we pick today's דף Daf is צ"ה. Tsadi Hey. We pick
up on the bottom of צ"ד עמוד ב Tsadi Dalet Amud Bet
and we are בעשרה
כולי עלמא לא פליגי. b'eser kulei alma lo peligi. It's four lines
from the bottom, two words before the end of the line.
And basically to review, the point of the משנה Mishnah had been
that if a wall falls down on שבת, Shabbos, then you can
still carry in the zone because it was מותר mutar when שבת
Shabbos began. That was the position of the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma,
of רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. And רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says, no,
you got to be consistent. Either it's going to be okay this,
you know, okay for future שבתות, Shabboses, or it's not going to
be okay this שבת. Shabbos. And we'll see in the גמרא Gemara
in a few minutes that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi basically says it's
not okay. So this is sort of the reverse of the principle
of, you know, well or whatever, of that we saw yesterday, or
the same principle of כיון דהותרה הותרה. keivan de'hutra hutra. Once it's
when that's... right, but you know, if it's הותרה לאותו שבת, hutra
le'ohto Shabbos, it's הותרה לכל השבת כולו. hutra lechol ha'Shabbos kulo. Once
it starts off okay, it remains okay for the whole שבת. Shabbos.
And similarly in the reverse, you know, about something become, you know,
changing its status for becoming more מותר mutar on שבת, Shabbos, but
anyway, this is the principle that we say that it continues the
way that it began. Now there's a limit to this because, you
know, if it becomes a real like רשות הרבים reshus ha'rabim or
something, we're not going to allow something biblical, even how much of
a rabbinic, you know, sort of status are we going to tolerate
is a question, which is why the גמרא, Gemara, although the case
in the משנה Mishnah spoke about two walls falling down, the גמרא
Gemara went to a lot of effort to explain that it doesn't
really mean two walls to the point that now this might become
like I don't know רשות הרבים, reshus ha'rabim, that we're really talking
about like some corner of a wall fell down, two edges, but
that really you have mostly three other walls, and had different types
of scenarios about that, and about why we had to say two
walls fell down since one wall would have been enough to have
lost its רשות היחיד reshus hayachid status and to have created the
scenario in the משנה. Mishnah. Okay, and within that we saw debate
between רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel about when do you say this
principle of פי תקרה יורד וסותם, pi tikra yored vesosem, that the
edge of a roof, if you have the, is considered to go
down and to create a wall and to seal off that side.
So according to the way רש"י Rashi read the גמרא, Gemara, רש"י
Rashi said that they debated between
that שמואל Shmuel said you can't say it for all walls,
but
you can say it once you have a few walls, at most
you can't say it for four walls is what שמואל'ס Shmuel's position
was.
Does it ever rely on the situation as it was when שבת
Shabbos began?
We're going to get to that in a minute, how we got
it. Okay, so anyway, תוספות Tosafos has a whole different read of
the גמרא. Gemara. But רש"י'ס Rashi's read is, is that according to
שמואל Shmuel you don't say פי תקרה pi tikra for four walls
and according to רב, Rav, you can say it even for a
full four walls. Okay, so that was like one debate. But now
the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to turn its attention to other parameters perhaps
of the debate of רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. So again, the
issue in the משנה Mishnah is that one or two walls fell
down and you can still use that zone on שבת Shabbos based
on the way it started. That's according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
And then the question is why did it have to say two,
since one wall would have been enough to have created the problem,
and that led to a whole conversation yesterday. But we ended with
a debate of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel about פי תקרה יורד
וסותם, pi tikra yored vesosem, that רב'ס Rav's more prepared to say
פי תקרה יורד וסותם pi tikra yored vesosem than שמואל Shmuel is.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, בעשרה כולי עלמא לא
פליגי, b'eser kulei alma lo peligi, everybody, nobody disagrees.
I'm
sorry,
בעשרה כולי עלמא לא פליגי, b'eser kulei alma lo peligi, four lines
from the bottom, if it's ten אמות amos or less the break,
nobody disagrees that you say פי תקרה יורד וסותם. pi tikra yored
vesosem. כי פליגי ביתר מעשרה, Ki peligi beyaser me'eser, the debate is
when it is a break more than ten, which is normally when
you need to say פי תקרה pi tikra because a break more
than ten אמות amos is not considered like an opening
and therefore you need to fix it and you need to address
it. And that's where they debate about whether you say פי תקרה
יורד וסותם pi tikra yored vesosem according to שמואל Shmuel on three
walls and according to רב Rav even by four walls. איכא דאמרי,
Ika de'amri, others say no, ביתר כולי עלמא לא פליגי, beyaser kulei
alma lo peligi, everybody, more than ten, nobody disagrees that you cannot
say פי תקרה. pi tikra. Okay, so this is a new twist
on פי תקרה, pi tikra, that maybe פי תקרה pi tikra does
not work for an opening that is too large. כי פליגי בעשרה,
Ki peligi b'eser, the debate is ten אמות amos or fewer. Only
there is it possible to say פי תקרה. pi tikra. So again,
the debate of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel is do you say
it with three walls or four walls, this is the way רש"י
Rashi says it, but the גמרא Gemara says, wait. When can you
say it? Either everybody agrees you can say it with a small
opening, the question is a big one or no, if it's a
big one everybody agrees you can't. The question is if it's ten
אמות amot or smaller, then can you say פי תקרה pi tikra
or not? Now you might ask if it's ten אמות amot or
smaller who needs פי תקרה, pi tikra, right? Because it's just considered
like an opening in the wall, an opening in the wall like
a door in the wall, it's not a problem. But it could
be a problem in two scenarios, actually maybe they boil down to
the same scenario. One is is that you have too many openings,
so it's like פרוץ מרובה על העומד, parutz meruba al ha-omed, right?
If you have too many openings, you've got a problem in itself.
And the other which is just an extreme of that example is
the case that רש״י Rashi described about the about the portico in
the middle of the valley where you actually have no walls. So
can you say פי תקרה pi tikra when the wall that it's
creating is bigger than ten אמות amot or not? That's the question
of the גמרא. Gemara. Is the is are פי תקרה pi tikra
an issue for ten אמות amot or smaller or even for greater
than ten אמות? amot?
Interesting to establish the premise, I would have thought that it depends
on on the number of breaks or piece forget about the width
of the break you know on the on the horizontal I say
on the you know I say on the vertical because how much
I mean as you think you know in other words depending on
how high the roof is from the ground floor.
Well that's an interesting ay that's an interesting question would you be
able to say פי תקרה pi tikra for example if it's higher
than twenty אמות amot going back to the beginning of our מסכת
masekhet when the roof is not even seen somehow in the context.
That's might be an interesting limit. I don't know if that's discussed.
Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
Okay. והא דאמר רב יהודה, ve-ha de-amar Rav Yehuda, that which רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda says קורה ארבע מטיא בחורבה, kora arba matya be-churva,
that if you have a wall a a beam that is four
four טפחים, tefachim, that creates its own רשות היחיד. reshut ha-yachid. So
you basically have this beam here and standing in the middle of
a of a like you know of an empty field. It's four
טפחים tefachim wide. This is going to create a רשות היחיד reshut
ha-yachid under it. Why? Because you use the edge of the beam
and say פי תקרה pi tikra on all four sides. Okay, this
is like רב Rav who says you can say פי תקרה pi
tikra on four sides and you have a space four by four
טפחים tefachim that's surrounded by walls. Okay, that is a real extreme
example of פי תקרה. pi tikra. Okay, so he says that. רב
נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה אמר רב נחמן Rav Nachman amar Rabba
bar Avuha amar Rav Nachman says in the name of רבה בר
אבוה Rabba bar Avuha קורה ארבע מטיא במים. kora arba matya be-mayim.
No,
only in the water as you remember we had special leniencies by
walls over water allowing you to draw from the water but we
would not apply it on dry land. מני, mani, who's that going
like? Certainly the first opinion that you can say it on all
four sides.
להך לישנא דאמרת בעשר לא פליגי, le-ha lishana de-amart be-esser lo pligi,
that ten אמות amot or smaller everybody agrees it's okay, דעשר
ודברי הכל, de-esser ve-divrei hakol, even שמואל Shmuel could agree. Because again
according to רש״י Rashi the debate of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel
is do you say it on four
sides and שמואל Shmuel says no I won't let you say it
on four sides. In this case the beam is a case of
four sides. But maybe שמואל Shmuel only disagrees with big openings, openings
ten or larger, I mean larger than ten. But openings ten or
smaller, everybody would agree not only that you say פי תקרה pi
tikra but you can even say it on all four sides. So
therefore this idea that the beam works, that could be even שמואל's
Shmuel position as long as it is as long as it is
less than ten אמות amot wide. That's one possibility. ואידך לישנא דאמרת
בעשר פליגי, ve-idach lishana de-amarta be-esser pligi, if the base that they
say they even debate ten or smaller so and so this has
to be you know even if it's smaller than ten that's still
the debate, then כרב, ke-Rav, then that idea that you would say
it on all four sides is going like רב. Rav. Okay. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. לימא אביי ורבא בפלוגתא דרב
ושמואל קא מיפלגי, leima Abaye ve-Rava bi-plugta de-Rav u-Shmuel ka miflegi, maybe
an a debate of אביי Abaye and רבא Rava parallels רב Rav
and שמואל Shmuel because רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel are debating you
know this portico in the valley, פי תקרה pi tikra on all
four sides and it seems like that's a debate of אביי Abaye
and רבא. Rava. דאתמר, de-itmar, it was taught, סככה גבי אכסדרא שיש
לה פצימין, sekhakha gabei achsadra she-yesh lah petzimim,
if somebody puts סכך s'chach on type of again this portico that
has posts, כשרה, keshera, it's kosher. אין לה פצימין, ein lah petzimim,
now again I don't know what happened to my markers, I think
I took them away. Anyway assuming this is your assuming that this
is your like portico, okay this is the wall here, right and
this is your wall and ach I don't know if you can
sort of see that anyway whatever it is. Do we have it
here? No we don't have a good picture there. Anyway you've got
something that's got that's got two walls and at the edges has
little posts that are little bits of a of a third and
a fourth wall. So if it has those little posts, right then
that makes it like two and a half walls which counts for
סוכה sukkah and everybody says it's okay. If you don't have those
walls, then you basically have just this open you know sided portico
or maybe you don't have any walls at all, maybe you just
have like posts and then again it's similar to that portico in
the valley here it's a question about סכך s'chach in a סוכה
sukkah but what do you do that you don't even have the
requisite walls and you need the requisite walls to be made to
use the פי תקרה, pi tikra, the edge of the סכך s'chach
to go down. Okay so אין לה פצימין, ein lah petzimim, if
it does not have these posts to make the requisite wall, אביי
אמר כשרה, Abaye amar keshera, it's still kosher, ורבא אמר פסולה, ve-Rava
amar pesula, it's pasul. So אביי אמר כשרה פי תקרה יורד וסותם,
Abaye amar keshera pi tikra yored ve-sotem, ורבא אמר פסולה לא אמרינן
פי תקרה יורד וסותם. ve-Rava amar pesula lo amrinan pi tikra yored
ve-sotem. So clearly they're debating some issue about the parameters of פי
תקרה. pi tikra. Maybe it's the issue of three walls versus four
walls and it's the debate of רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. לימא
אביי כרב, leima Abaye ke-Rav, let's say it's talking about a
four
wall. כי פליגי, ki pligi, what's their debate of אביי Abaye and
רבא Rava אליבא דרב? aliba d'Rav? According to רב, Rav, who says
normally you can say it by four walls in the case of
the portico. אליבא דרב, aliba d'Rav, אביי כרב. Abaye k'Rav. אביי Abaye
says, look, רב Rav says you can say it by four walls
by רשות היחיד reshus hayachid over there, you can say it also
by סכך. skach. ורבא, v'Rava, and רבא Rava would say, no, not
so fast. עד כאן לא קאמר רב התם, ad kan lo kamar
Rav hasam, רב Rav only says there that you can say it
by four walls אלא דהני מחיצות לאכסדרה עבידי, ela dehani mechitos l'achsadra
avidi, the מחיצות, mechitos, now there aren't מחיצות, mechitos, the way רש"י
Rashi says it means it's the roof, the roof is made for
the portico. That case that you have a portico that has naturally
built a roof on it, you know, it's built with a roof,
so the roof is there for the sake, you know, for that's
the structure for a roof. And presumably the logic I should say
of פי תקרה, pi tikra, the way I understand the logic is,
is that it's a lot easier to sort of imagine this as
a walled structure when something has a roof. A roof suggests walls.
I think that is maybe for me a way of saying it,
which is why if you remember פי תקרה pi tikra works more
effectively than actually having a wall. Having a suspended wall that doesn't
go all the way down. פי תקרה pi tikra does, because the
פי תקרה pi tikra basically already, you know, creates some type of
defined space underneath the ceiling and suggests a sense of an enclosed
space. So therefore here when you have a portico and you've got
the roof that it's built with, that it's more easy to say
פי תקרה. pi tikra. But in our case, you really just had
posts and you put סכך skach on it, which means naturally there's
no roof on it. So for this type of a temporary ad
hoc roof made for the purpose of סוכה sukka to be able
to say פי תקרה pi tikra there, to say it for all
four walls, that's where we'll draw the line. Okay. אלא דהני מחיצות
לאכסדרה עבידי והכא הני מחיצות, ela dehani mechitos l'achsadra avidi vehacha hani
mechitos, the מחיצות, mechitos, meaning the מחיצות mechitos created for the, from
the, from the roof, from the סכך, skach, לאו לסוכה עבידי, lav
l'sukka avidi, is not made for the סוכה, sukka, לא, lo, you
wouldn't say. Now of course it doesn't really mean wasn't made for
the סוכה, sukka, you put the סכך skach on for the sake
of סוכות, Sukkos, okay, but what it means is, the way I
would understand it is, is that it's not basically a structure that
generally is a structure with a roof that defines the space underneath
it. That was only created ad hoc and therefore that's not strong
enough to say פי תקרה pi tikra on all four sides. So
here according to רש"י Rashi we have this debate of do you
say פי תקרה pi tikra on four sides or three sides, debate
of רבא Rava and שמואל, Shmuel, is maybe it's better if it's
ten אמות amot or less, maybe everybody would say it's okay, and
then the issue about would it be different if the roof was
made it was a regular roof made for that or an ad
hoc roof. Now the גמרא Gemara moves on to רבי יוסי, Rabbi
Yosi, back to the main point of the משנה, Mishna, getting to
the question of how do we פסקן, pasken, though playing the role
of Michael for today. So the issue about what happens if a
wall falls down, this is really the point of the משנה, Mishna,
can you keep on using that space on שבת, Shabbos, and the
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says yes and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says
no. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
איבעיא להו, ibayu lehu, they raised the question. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi
לאיסורא או להתירא? l'issura o l'hetera? Is רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi saying
that if it's מותר mutar now it's going to be מותר mutar
here on in or is he saying that that's להתירא l'hetera or
is he saying לאיסורא l'issura that since it's not good for future
שבתes Shabbos it's not good for this one? אמר רב ששת לאיסורא,
amar Rav Sheshet l'issura, וכן אמר רבי יוחנן לאיסורא. vechen amar Rabbi
Yochanan l'issura. Right, because it would be pretty strange, I mean I
don't think you just oh but they tend to be מחמיר machmir
because actually in עירוב eruv we tend to be מקיל, meikel, but
it would be pretty strange that just because you had an accident
one שבת Shabbos we're now going to go more easy on you
in future שבתes. Shabbos Right, this is a violation of the normal
rule, so obviously what should dictate is the normal rule. תניא נמי
הכי, tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly, אמר רבי יוסי כשם שאסורה
לעתיד לבוא כך אסורה לאותה שבת, amar Rabbi Yosi k'shem she'asura l'asid
lavo kach asura l'osa Shabbos, the same way it's going to be
a problem in the future, it's a problem now. Now we get
to the question of how do we פסקן. pasken. So
איתמר, itmar, it was taught, רב חייא בר יוסף אמר הלכה כרבי
יוסי,
Rav Chiya bar Yosef amar halacha
k'Rabbi Yosi,
we rule like רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. ושמואל אמר הלכה כרבי יהודה,
v'Shmuel amar halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda, שמואל Shmuel says we rule like רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
that it stays good. So now the גמרא Gemara says ומי אמר
שמואל הכי, u'mi amar Shmuel hachi, did שמואל Shmuel really say we
go like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and that it's good? והתנן, v'hasnan,
אמר רב יהודה, amar Rav Yehuda, this is שמואל's Shmuel תלמיד, talmid,
no
I'm sorry this אמר רבי יהודה, amar Rebbi Yehuda, excuse me, רב
יהודה's Rav Yehuda coming up. אמר רבי יהודה במה דברים אמורים, amar
Rebbi Yehuda bamei devarim amurim, when is it true that you can
make an עירוב eruv for somebody else without their knowledge, בעירובי תחומין,
bei eruvei techumin, when it's עירוב, eruv, I'm sorry,
when can you not make an עירוב eruv for somebody without their
knowledge, by an עירובי תחומין eruvei techumin because anytime you make an
עירוב eruv for them in one direction they lose on the other
side. אבל בעירובי חצרות, aval bei eruvei chatzeros, but by עירובי חצרות,
eruvei chatzeros, מערבין בין לדעת בין שלא לדעת, me'arvin bein l'da'as bein
shelo l'da'as, you can do it whether they're aware or not aware
for their behalf, לפי שזכין לאדם שלא בפניו, lefi she'zakhin l'adam shelo
befanav, you can bring merit to a person when they're not present.
When can you not make an עירוב eruv for somebody without their
knowledge? By עירוב תחומין Eruv Techumin because any time you make an
עירוב eruv for them in one direction, they lose on the other
side. אבל בעירובי חצרות, Aval b'Eruvei Chatzerot, but by עירובי חצרות, Eruvei
Chatzerot, מערבין בין לדעת בין שלא לדעת, me'arvin bein l'da'at bein shelo
l'da'at, you can do it whether they're aware or not aware for
their behalf, לפי שזכין לאדם שלא בפניו, lefi she'zachin l'adam shelo b'fanav,
you can bring merit to somebody not in their presence, so you
can benefit him by making an עירוב תחומין, Eruv Techumin, an עירובי
חצרות Eruvei Chatzeros which only helps him, not in his presence and
not with his awareness, וחבין v'chavin but you could not injure a
person שלא בפניו shelo b'fanav not in their presence, not with their
awareness, and therefore even a mixed thing that has a benefit on
one side and a detriment on the other, you cannot do without
their awareness. Okay, very reasonable position, and you can make an עירוב
תחומין eruv techumin for him, an עירובי חצרות eruvei chatzeros for him
without his awareness. ואמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, V'amar Rav Yehuda amar
Shmuel, Rav Yehuda says in the name of Shmuel, הלכה כרבי יהודה,
halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda, we rule like Rabbi Yehuda that you can make
an עירוב חצרות eruv chatzeros without the person's awareness, which is probably
before we started learning עירובין, Eruvin, a lot of people might not
have been aware that the eruv that works in the community is
not just the צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach which makes the walls, but
the fact that the rabbi once a year takes a box of
matzos for the whole community and he does exactly that, he makes
an עירוב חצרות שלא בפניו. eruv chatzeros shelo b'fanav. So we rule
like
Rabbi Yehuda. ולא עוד V'lo od and not only that, אלא כל
מקום ששנה רבי יהודה בעירובין הלכה כמותו, ela kol makom sheshana Rabbi
Yehuda b'Eruvin halacha k'moso,
wherever Rabbi Yehuda has a position in Eruvin we rule like him.
Now this seems to be consistent with the idea that Shmuel says
we pasken like Rabbi Yehuda. Why is the Gemara bringing this as
a challenge? Because of the next line. ואמר ליה רב חנא בגדתאה
לרב יהודה, V'amar lei Rav Chana Bagdata'ah l'Rav Yehuda, so Rav Chana
Bagdata'ah said back to Rav Yehuda, אמר שמואל אפילו במבוי שניטל קורתו
או לחייו, amar Shmuel afilu b'mavoi shenitla koraso o lechayav, if you
say Rabbi Yehuda always goes like, Shmuel always goes like Rabbi Yehuda,
would he even go like the Rabbi Yehuda of our mishna where
the like one of the walls fell down or the post or
the beam fell down and you didn't have the requisite wall configuration?
Would he even there go like Rabbi Yehuda and say that it
remains good? So אמר ליה amar lei and Shmuel said back to
him, בעירובין אמרי לך, b'Eruvin amri lach, no, no, no, I said
we rule like Rabbi Yehuda, Shmuel rules like Rabbi Yehuda in Eruvin
הלכות, halachos, ולא במחיצות, v'lo b'mechitzos, not in walls. Now again, we
tend to call all of it Eruvin because it lets you carry,
and the Gemara every now and then sort of seem to do
it the same, but technically, as you know, the issue of walls
is more a שבת Shabbos issue defining it as a רשות היחיד,
reshus hayachid, and the Eruvin is all about getting together in the
bread and in the food and creating that sense, that unity. So
he says no, no, no, Shmuel would not rule like Rabbi Yehuda
when actually a wall fell down. Okay, so that's, so we said
a minute ago Shmuel said we rule like Rabbi Yehuda, and our
mishna was a wall fell down and here Rav Yehuda is saying
that he wouldn't say like Rabbi Yehuda that way, so what's the
story?
So אמר רב אבא amar Rav Abba לדידי מפרשא לי מיניה דשמואל,
l'didi mefarsha li minei d'Shmuel, it was explained to me in the
name of Shmuel that it depends what the scenario
is. כאן שנפרצו לכרמלית כאן שנפרצו לרשות הרבים. Kan shenifretzu l'karmelis, kan
shenifretzu l'reshus harabbim. If the חצר, chatzer, the wall fell down and
it's exposed to a כרמלית, karmelis, so it does not, there's not
really so much to be worried about. Even if you take carry
from the חצר chatzer to the כרמלית, karmelis, you're only, it's only
a rabbinic transgression, and therefore we'll allow it to remain good over
Shabbos. If it's exposed, I know sometimes, if the wall fell down
or, you know, the opening which had the beam and the beam
fell down opens to a רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, we're concerned there
it might lead to a biblical transgression from carrying from the חצר
chatzer to רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. By the way, I should mention
as opposed to our mishna whose concern is basically you don't have
the full number of walls, this is the concern at the opening
of the מבוי mavoi for the beam or the post, the לחי
lechi or the קורה, kora, which might be a wall idea but
it might be a היכר heker idea. Part of its primary function
is to remind you you are traveling into the DMZ or whatever
it is, you're about to travel into a new zone. So therefore
when that falls down, the immediate concern is how bad is that
new zone. If that new zone is a רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim,
then we can't let this continue even if it happened on Shabbos.
If that zone that you might walk into is a כרמלית, karmelis,
then we can. So we'll go like Rabbi Yehuda and we'll retain
it okay presumably in two scenarios, I want to say, which is
not clear, I'm repeating this because it's not so clear from the
mishna. Number one is is that there are still three full walls,
our mishna talks about two walls falling down. And number two is
is that the only zone that it's open to is a כרמלית.
karmelis. That's where he'll say we'll rule like Rabbi Yehuda.
Otherwise, it's all that it fell, no, all is that it did
fall down on Shabbos, right. And even, no, but even so only
if there are three full walls and that the zone it's open
to is a כרמלית. karmelis. So that's not a big פסק psak
like Rabbi Yehuda, it's a very narrow case. And anyway, we had
the other פסק psak which was like רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi. So
תוספות Tosafot says who do we go like? We go like
the one who paskens like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi or Shmuel who
paskens like a modified Rabbi Yehuda. So if you look at תוספות,
Tosafot, ושמואל אמר לך כרבי יהודה, v'Shmuel amar lach k'Rabbi Yehuda, וסמוך
מוקי לה בנפרצו לכרמלית, v'samuch moki lah b'nifretzu l'karmelis, וניראה דהלכה כרב
באיסורי. v'nir'eh d'halacha k'Rav b'issurei. It
doesn't matter anyway. We pasken like Rav against Shmuel. ואפילו בנפרצה לכרמלית
הלכה כרבי יוסי
דמחמיר. V'afilu b'nifretza l'karmelis halacha k'Rabbi Yossi d'machmir. All right, anyway so
that's your question about the פסק הלכה. psak halacha.
Did we have a question? Yes, so the, but the principle of
how it was before Shabbos is the way that it remains regardless
of what happens in, under the circumstances, yes, is intact.
Yes. Yes. And certainly it's true when we're not talking about walls
falling down, but we're talking about like עירובין eiruvin issues, or the
wall between two חצרות chatzeros fell down, you know, but that has
an עירוב eiruv implication, not a requisite number of walls implication.
So my question was in places where there's a concern sometimes about
the עירוב eiruv coming down on שבת, Shabbos, my impression is that
it's not broadcast because מוטב יהיו שוגגין ואל יהיו מזידין. mutav ihyu
shogegin v'al ihyu mezidin.
That's true, but fundamentally it
doesn't even seem relevant because in most... I'm sure in most cases
these conditions would probably be fulfilled and so...
no, because first of all שמואל Shmuel says, as תוספות Tosafot we
פוסקן pasken like רב, Rav, so... what would that have to do
with this
discussion?
Because רב Rav פוסקן pasken like רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi.
I
thought it was רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiya. אמר רבי חייא בר אשי
אמר רב, Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Ashi amar Rav, which is if
you look at the side, which is תוספות's Tosafot גרסא. girsa. So
anyway, first of all, that's number one, and number two, I don't
know, it's a good question. When the עירוב eiruv does go down,
you're right, it probably only creates a small breach, like it depends
if it's a serious storm. But right, but if you... it's a
good point, very often the עירוב eiruv goes down and you still
have like three and three quarters walls and it really wouldn't be
an issue at all. So I don't know why you're right they
use the argument of מוטב יהיו שוגגין. mutav ihyu shogegin. I assume
there are sometimes it really goes down and it really, you know,
does get fewer than the minimum number of walls. But it's true,
I mean, even רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi who is מחמיר machmir is
only when you fall below the minimum. Our עירוב eiruv is like
completely surrounds the whole space. It's possible for a section to fall
down and still be 100% כשר. kasher. Yes. Different question.
רב חנא בגדתא Rav Chana Bagdata to Baghdad or something? Yeah, Baghdad
was founded in the 7th century by the Arabs.
Oh, so it can't be Baghdad then. It's got to be another
place. Alright, let's look at the next משנה. Mishna. Finish up this
פרק. Perek. הבונה עליה על
גבי שני בתים. Haboneh aliyah al gabi sheni batim. If you have
a house over that's over two... a second story that's over two
houses. You have two houses on two sides of the רשות הרבים
reshut harabbim and you go ahead and you build your house on
top of them. So you've got a house here on one side
of רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, a house here on the other and
you build a like you know an... like one of those yeah
like a bridge essentially like you know in Manhattan you get those
a lot those bridges you know that you know that walkway right
the walkway over a highway. It's exactly what that is. And you
made that though as an עליה. aliyah. Okay that's true. But okay
וכן גשרים המפולשים v'chen gisharim hamfulashim
or a bridge that goes over that's open at both ends but
it's got walls on the two sides, the walls of the houses,
and it's over it's over רשות הרבים reshut harabbim מטלטלין תחתיהן בשבת
דברי רבי יהודה. mtaltelin tachteihen b'shabbat divrei Rabbi Yehudah. You can carry
under them. Now one reason you would say you could do this
is פי תקרה יורד וסותם. pi tikrah yored v'sotem. Right the edges
go down and you have the two real walls on the side
the walls of the houses which are creating the others and then
the two walls of the bridge. וחכמים אומרים, vachachamim omrim, the חכמים
Chachamim say אסור assur it's forbidden. ועוד אמר רבי יהודה v'od amar
Rabbi Yehudah and further said רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah מערבין למבוי מפולש
m'arvin l'mavoi mefulash if for that you have a ceiling even if
you just have an open-ended street okay so it's got walls on
two sides but the other you know the long sides have walls
but the ends are unwalled. מפולש mefulash on both sides right? Yeah
meaning that מפולש mefulash means as opposed to סתום satum means there's
a wall here and a wall here but it's a it goes
straight through it's not a dead end street that you can actually
you can actually make an עירוב eiruv there you can turn that
into a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid and carry in it. וחכמים אוסרין
vachachamim osrin the חכמים Chachamim forbid. So by the end of the
משנה Mishna we see that even without פי תקרה pi tikrah he
allows two walls to suffice and this is an idea we had
way earlier that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah basically says two walls is
enough to make something a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. Okay so let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רבה Amar Rabbah said
רבה Rabbah לא תימא היינו טעמא דרבי יהודה משום דקסבר שתי מחיצות
דאורייתא lo teima hainu ta'ama d'Rabbi Yehudah mishum d'kasvar shtei mechitzot d'oraita
don't think the reason at least of the first part of the
משנה Mishna of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah is because two מחיצות mechitzot
is enough biblically and you don't and you know and you have
it for the houses on the two sides of the street אלא
משום דקסבר פי תקרה יורד וסותם ela mishum d'kasvar pi tikrah yored
v'sotem the reason of the משנה Mishna is because of the edges
of the of the second of the you know the עליה aliyah
of the walkway or of the bridge go down and actually make
four walls. איתיביה אביי Eitivei Abaye אביי Abaye said one minute you
can't say that he doesn't hold two walls suffices. I'll show you
two walls do suffice according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehudah. יתר על
כן אמר רבי יהודה Yeter al ken amar Rabbi Yehudah רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehudah went even further and he said based on of from
another discussion מי שיש לו שני בתים משני צידי רשות הרבים mi
sheyesh lo sheni batim mishnei tziadei reshut harabbim you have two houses
on two sides of the רשות הרבים reshut harabbim so those two
houses create walls alongside a small section of the רשות הרבים reshut
harabbim עושה לחי מכאן ולחי מכאן או קורה מכאן וקורה מכאן oseh
lechi mikan u'lechi mikan o korah mikan v'korah mikan you either put
a לחי lechi post on either side or a קורה korah beam
on either side of the you know of the actual of the
open ends ונושא
ונותן באמצע v'noseh v'noten ba'emtza and you can carry in the middle
so it's wild you can have a real רשות הרבים reshut harabbim
that has a small section that has a wall on each side
and you make a tiny little post or a beam to make
it a sort of some type of a you know demarcator and
that's enough. So basically... You have two walls already makes it into
a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. אמרו לו, amru lo, they said to
him, אין מערבין ברשות הרבים בכך, ain me’arvin b’reshus harabim b’kach, I'm
sorry, that can’t, you can’t make an עירוב eruv in a רשות
הרבים reshus harabim with that flimsy number of walls.
אמר ליה, amar leh, so you see anyway that two walls work
for Reb Yehuda without פי תקרה. pi tikrah. אמר ליה, amar leh,
מהא דין, me’ha din, yes, you're right, I'm not arguing what Reb
Yehuda's position is. I know Reb Yehuda holds two walls and from
that case over there about the two houses on the two sides
of רשות הרבים reshus harabim that all you need is a לחי
lechi or a קורה, korah, you're right, it's clear two walls suffices.
מהא ליכא למשמע מינה. me’ha leka l’mishma mina. What I'm saying is
that from the משנה mishnah it's not clear that that's his position
because from the משנה mishnah it could be that the bridge created
the walls and not the two walls suffices. So of course he's
sort of it's an academic debate. It's a purely academic debate. I
totally know where Reb Yehuda's position is, but I just want to
point out that in the beginning of the משנה mishnah it could
have been understood to have been about פי תקרה. pi tikrah. So
אמר רב אשי, amar rav ashi, מתניתין נמי דיקא, masnisin nami dika,
you know what? From our משנה mishnah it's also clear that the
first line is not about the two walls, that that's only the
second case in the משנה. mishnah. מדקתני midekatani since the second case
says ועוד אמר רבי יהודה, ve’od amar reb yehuda, מערבין במבוי מפולש,
me’arvin b’mavo mefulash, וחכמים אוסרין, ve’chachamim osrin,
that Reb Yehuda says you can even make an עירוב eruv in
an open-ended street and the חכמים chachamim say you can't. So there
clearly it's an open-ended street with no roof. There clearly it's about
two walls. So אי אמרת בשלמא משום דקסבר פי תקרה יורד וסותם,
ei amart bishlama mishum dekasavar pi tikrah yored vesosem,
if the first case in the משנה mishnah is based on פי
תקרה יורד וסותם, pi tikrah yored vesosem, היינו דקתני ועוד, hainu dekatani
ve’od, that's why it says and you know what, Reb Yehuda doesn't
even need פי תקרה, pi tikrah, he even allows it with just
two walls. אלא אי אמרת משום דקסבר שתי מחיצות, ela ei amart
mishum dekasavar shtei mechitzos, right, if the first case in the משנה
mishnah was based on the idea of two walls, מאי ועוד, mai
ve’od, why does he have to give me the second case? שמע
מינה. shma mina. So you hear that. So basically as Michael said,
it's pretty academic because we know Reb Yehuda two walls suffices. He's
just saying the first case in the משנה mishnah didn't have to
rely on that, it could have relied on פי תקרה. pi tikrah.
And the interesting question is since we've been learning פי תקרה pi
tikrah and this is why maybe it's not academic is that since
we have פי תקרה pi tikrah on the first case of the
משנה, mishnah, it raises the question why the חכמים chachamim don't allow
it. I get that the חכמים chachamim don't allow two walls, but
since everybody's been holding variations of פי תקרה, pi tikrah, why do
the חכמים chachamim disagree right in the משנה? mishnah? And that is
not clear and that question is put on the table if we
emphasize that Reb Yehuda is also has פי תקרה pi tikrah to
back him up. And presumably the answer to that is is that
here it's sort of it's a פי תקרה pi tikrah that's constantly
being violated, that's going through the middle of like of a רשות
הרבים reshus harabim or of a מבוי. mavo. Right, we added about
a פי תקרה pi tikrah in the middle of a yard, in
the middle of a valley. So but here you got you're imagining
invisible walls that every second people are driving through. Okay, so presumably
that's the debate in the משנה, mishnah, can you say פי תקרה
pi tikrah there? And then Reb Yehuda says you know what? A,
I think you could say פי תקרה pi tikrah there and even
if you couldn't say פי תקרה, pi tikrah, I'm going to be
okay with it because I say two walls is enough. הדרן עלך
כל הגגות. hadran alach kol hagagos. That is the end of that
perek. I hope that as Dov said I've been promising you things
are going to get different. That perek was a little different. I
do think it was not it was actually scenarios where you didn't
make an עירוב eruv and it was talking about how to deal
with it and then we also got into some רשות היחיד reshus
hayachid and wall issues. So it was I think a nice change.
And the last perek is significantly different and that's המוציא תפילין. hamotzi
tefillin. So we'll start reading and you'll see how it's a completely
different case, so much to the point that תוספות tosafos asks what's
it doing in this מסכת? maseches? Let's take a look. I'll tell
you in a minute. Let's first see what it's about. המוציא תפילין,
hamotzi tefillin, if somebody finds תפילין tefillin out of the middle of
the street, forget חוץ לתחום chutz l’tchum on שבת. shabbos. It is
שבת. shabbos. Right, not that different. Okay.
So it's in a yard, it's in a field, there's no walls,
there's no עירוב, eruv, there's no nothing. You find תפילין tefillin in
the middle of the street, what do you do? מכניסן זוג זוג.
machnisan zug zug. You put the you bring them in pair by
pair. You put on a pair, the של יד shel yad and
the של ראש, shel rosh, you wear it, you bring it home,
you take it off, you go back and you wear another pair
back and forth.
So it doesn't mean just wear the יד yad or just wear
the ראש? rosh?
No, every each a full pair. רבן גמליאל אומר, שנים שנים. Rabban
Gamliel omer shenayim shenayim. You can actually wear two pairs at the
same time, two של ידס shel yads and two של ראשס. shel
roshes. Like רש"י rashi and רבנו תם. rabbeinu tam.
Right, exactly. Let's see about this in מחיצות. mechitzos. במה דברים אמורים,
bameh devarim amurim, בישנות, biyashanos, בישנות, biyashanos, excuse me, I knew I
was going to do that wrong. בישנות—they're biyashanos sleeping? —אבל בחדשות פטור.
aval bachadashos patur.
That's if they're old תפילין, tefillin, meaning they're used and you can
somehow tell that they are הלכתי halachic תפילין. tefillin. But if they're
brand new, you are exempt and not just exempt but forbidden to
do this trick. Why? Who cares if they're new? So if they're
new, apparently it was very common at that time to make amulets,
as we know, and amulets would be put into some type of
a special container and wrapped on parts of the body. And therefore
very something that looked like תפילין tefillin could actually be not really
תפילין tefillin but an amulet. Now of course it's a little hard
for us to imagine that somebody would make an amulet that looked
exactly like
a תפילין, tefillin, the perfect square and the whatever. So but but
you know. Maybe also was as we know from other cases that
the rabbis had serious debates with the צדוקים Tsadukim or whatever of
exactly issues around what תפילין tefillin looked like and other aspects of
the תפילין tefillin because so much of the specifics is not in
the תורה Torah at all about the תפילין. tefillin. So presumably there
is some concern that if they are not worn and used that
they might be something other than הלכתי halakhic תפילין. tefillin.
But if the משנה Mishnah says tefillin make on amulets.
Yes, if you happen to be wearing them or whatever, there is
something you're finding and you're doing this as a trick of doing
this as a way of getting them indoors to protect them.
Why not מזוזה? mezuzah? Because you can't wear it.
That's an interesting question. Right, so we'll see in a minute about
things you can do when wearing it is not an option. Okay,
so we'll see cases like that by תפילין, tefillin, yes, similar thing.
I understand the function of an amulet. First of all, how can
you tell if it's an amulet or תפילין tefillin based on how
it's used?
Yeah, I was sort of wondering that too.
And also aren't amulets worn?
Well,
aren't amulets worn? That's Michael's question. So first of all רשי Rashi
says according to your question about how does newer versus old matter,
רשי Rashi says that the used ones mean that the knots were
made. So you see like the דלת dalet of the head and
you see maybe the יוד yud of the של יד, shel yad,
so maybe that nobody would make for an amulet. So meaning you're
finding so presumably for רשי Rashi the real difference seems to be
is it just the box or is it the box with the
straps and the straps with the קשר kesher and therefore you know
that it's תפילין. tefillin. That's the way רשי Rashi explains it. In
terms of the issue of can't you just wear an amulet, the
answer is yes, but you're not really wearing this, I mean you
know that was debated or whatever, and that's when you're doing it
for רפואה refuah here you're doing it anyway, but even assuming you
could, you know here you're doing it as a trick of transporting
them back in. So did they allow you to do this trick
that they're not allowing you...
But you said you wear the rest of שבת Shabbat or whatever,
right?
If you found this amulet on the street and you found a
necklace on the street and you said great, you know, I pick
it up and put it on and wear it, yeah, of course,
that you could do. Okay. Now מצאן צבתים matsan tsvatim או כריכות,
o kerikhot, if you found them in like bound together or in
bundles,
then there's again a similar concern about whether they are actual you
know you can actually wear them. Then מחשיך עליהם ומביאן, makhshikh aleihem
u-mevian, then you wait there for nightfall and you bring them home
but you don't actually wear them. Now it's not exactly clear why
not, you know, why don't you just get them out of their
bundle, but anyway, but we will see about that in the גמרא.
Gemara.
Okay. Wait, so the cases before nightfall, this is like בין השמשות?
bein ha-shmashot? No no, no no, this is you found them at
six AM, but this is a scenario and it gets to Rivka's
point where you can't wear them. It's not clear why you can't
wear them. You mean מוצאי שבת? Motzaei Shabbat? Yes, you wait till
it's Saturday night and then you stand around there all day and
actually the point is not just you're allowed but the point of
the משנה Mishnah is similar to the point before about פטור, patur,
you're obligated. You see these תפילין tefillin that could be you know
that are that have the potential of being ביזיון bizayon about being
you know mistreated and stolen, you have an obligation to stand there
and watch them. Okay, so why you can't wear them we'll see.
ובסכנה, u-vi-sakkanah, now if it's a time of danger, now again סכנה
sakkanah sometimes means like you know concern about non-Jewish oppression, but here
presumably it just means who wants to be out in the middle
of the field until it gets מוצאי שבת Motzaei Shabbat an hour
after sunset. Okay, so you don't want to stay you're concerned for
your safety. In that case מכסן והולך לו, mekhasan ve-holekh lo, cover
them up and you're exempt from having to worry about them and
מוצאי שבת Motzaei Shabbat presumably you'll go and hopefully they'll still be
there.
So סכנה sakkanah for people, not a סכנה sakkanah is going to
happen to the תפילין. tefillin.
There is a סכנה sakkanah to happen to the תפילין tefillin but
we're more concerned about you than we're concerned about the
תפילין. tefillin. רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, נותן לחברו וחברו לחברו
עד שמגיע לחצר החיצונה. noten le-khavero ve-khavero le-khavero ad she-magia le-khatzer ha-khitzonah.
He says this might remind you of almost the last פרק perek
in שבת Shabbat as well, you're caught outside the city with your
wallet, right? So here what you do is, here's how we'll do
it. You call over a hundred people and we'll do a what's
it called Chinese fire drill, okay, and I take the תפילין tefillin
and I go to you and you go to the other guy
and you go to the other guy, nobody carries it more than
ארבע אמות, arba amot, and then even if it's a רשות הרבים,
reshut ha-rabim, and then we get it to the outer yard. Now
the outer yard has to be a yard not surrounded by walls
because then you're going from רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim into a רשות
היחיד. reshut ha-yakhid. Okay, but anyway you get it to some place
where it can be protected in the city and again assuming you
are not going from a רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim to a רשות
היחיד. reshut ha-yakhid. Okay, so that's what
you do.
וכן בנו, ve-khen beno,
similarly your son. What? What does that mean? So look at רשי,
Rashi, וכן בנו, ve-khen beno, last wide line of רשי, Rashi, שיולדתו
עמו שם בשדה בשבת. she-yoldato imo sham ba-sadeh be-Shabbat.
The mother, you know, brings you into the realities of what things
was, right, the mother was out in the field, I don't know
why she was at all, but you know all of a sudden
it's like people
who give birth in the taxi cab on the way to the
hospital, and so now you have an infant. What are you going
to do about this infant? How are you going to carry it?
And you can't say חי נושא את עצמו. chai noseh et atzmo.
Right, what do you need all that? Right, so clearly by the
infant, the סכנת נפשות sakkanat nefashot would override.
Well, we also have the תחום tchum home. We also have, well,
that's
true too. וחברו לחברו אפילו מאה Va'chavero l'chavero afilu me'ah and again
even you make a chain of a hundred people. רבי יהודה אומר
Rabbi Yehuda omer
נותן אדם חבילו לחברו noten adam chavilo l'chavero וחברו לחברו אפילו חוץ
לתחום. v'chavero l'chavero afilu chutz la'tchum.
You know what? If we're going to allow it by תפילין tefillin
and a baby, we could actually allow it even you know even
for property, which is a big jump. So I find a barrel
of wine out there, I left my barrel of wine out in
the yard and now it's going to I don't know thunderstorm or
whatever it's going to get destroyed, I can do this whole daisy
chain and get this thing back into a safe place, essentially again
assuming that I'm not going I'm not crossing the line into a
רשות היחיד. reshut ha-yachid. But not only that he adds not only
can you do it for property but even if the barrel was
outside of the תחום. tchum. So you're moving the barrel you know
crossing a תחום tchum line for the barrel. So אמרו לו amru
lo and this way it does bring it back to עירובין Eruvin
לא תהלך זו יותר מרגלי בעליה. lo teileich zo yoter me'raglei be'aleha.
It can't go further than the owner can go. Okay, so there's
an idea that we've seen before which we haven't elaborated on too
much but this idea the תחומים tchumim apply to my objects as
well. Okay, so if for example if I start off here and
the barrel is in the field and it's over here and the
safe spot is over there you can't take the barrel across the
תחום tchum line to protect it because it's going further than I
can go. Okay, but the amazing thing is besides that he's allowing
the תחום tchum issue is that he also even allows it just
for property and in that way it really does evoke the last
פרק perek of שבת Shabbos or the second to last I don't
remember anyway which is being caught outside of the city with your
wallet and ways in which we know that you will you know
for property issues we have to find leniencies or else you know
you'll come to even a greater violation. Now in terms of what
this is doing in this מסכת, masechet, תוספות Tosafot says it's because
of this last line of תחום tchum issues is why it's in
this מסכת. masechet. Why not earlier? I could say that it could
fit in because if you think about it the פרק perek we
just finished was about what do you do with no עירוב eruv
and yet you can still go from חצר chatzer to חצר chatzer
and from גג gag to גג gag with no עירוב. eruv. And
this in a way is not only if you don't have an
עירוב eruv what do you do if you don't have walls and
you still have something that needs to be transported and how do
you deal with that situation? So there is some way I think
it's thematically connected to the previous פרק perek yes Baruch.
It doesn't specifically say whether you're finding the תפילין tefillin or the
barrel in a רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim or a כרמלית. karmelit. Why
wouldn't he be able to take a תפילין tefillin into רשות היחיד
reshut ha-yachid if you found it out in the כרמלית? karmelit?
Because that's
well can you just directly go against the דרבנן de-rabbanan of רשות
הרבים reshut ha-rabim to כרמלית karmelit for example? Or a better question
also is can you get it from a רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim
to a כרמלית karmelit and then from a כרמלית karmelit into a
רשות היחיד reshut ha-yachid where it can really be protected? So so
far we haven't seen that so far everything you're doing is a
trick but it's not an outright violation, right? You're allowed to go
less than four אמות, amot, you're allowed to wear תפילין, tefillin, okay?
What you're asking is can you actually allow an outright violation of
a דרבנן? de-rabbanan? We haven't seen that yet, but we have a
פרק perek left to figure this out. Okay yes Rivka?
I'm troubled with this baby.
Right. A newborn baby.
Yes, it's סכנה sakana clearly. So why why even bother with this?
Why mention it? It seems so clear that the woman baby.
I know I don't know. No, you're right, you're right, it seems
much more obvious. Let's wait until we get to it in the
גמרא Gemara but I understand the issue.
Why do they interpret this as a newborn?
Well that's what רש"י Rashi said. I guess the other question is
I mean maybe it's just a question that you took your infant
out into the field before שבת Shabbos and you're playing and then
it got dark and you're stuck and it's like that would be
you're right that would be right right right
just a scenario of that's a child it's not a life.
Right. Yeah, you're right that you're right it's רש"י Rashi that says
it's a newborn.
Right. Okay. Okay, good point. We'll see it when we get to
it in the גמרא, Gemara, not today, but you are right רש"י
Rashi is the one that says newborn you didn't have to say
newborn which obviously heightens the stakes.
Is רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon saying you shouldn't wear the תפילין tefillin
or saying there's another option?
No
no no that was a case where you weren't able to wear
the תפילין. tefillin. That was the case about the bundle. We don't
know why you can't but he was talking about a case where
you couldn't.
Oh so he's agreeing מחמיר machmir and he's saying you can put
it in.
Right.
Okay, everybody please. We'll talk about the baby later.
Thank you. Okay, זוג אחד ולא שתיים. zug echad v'lo shtayim.
So only one pair at a time. So the whole issue about
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon covering it and getting dark and you know
the daisy chain was when you couldn't wear it back. But and
why not not clear we'll get to that. But in the first
case you can wear it. So the debate is can you wear
one pair or two pairs? So now we're going to try to
get to the heart of that debate. זוג אחד ולא שתיים. zug
echad v'lo shtayim. So לימא מתניתין דלא כרבי מאיר. leima matnitin d'lo
ke'Rabbi Meir. This idea that only one pair not two maybe this
is against רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Now which רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir?
דאי רבי מאיר הא אמר de-ei Rabbi Meir ha-amar we know that
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says in another case where you're sort of
cheating exactly where you are cheating tricking. and carrying stuff by wearing
it, that he actually says you can wear a lot, a lot
beyond the normal thing that you would wear. האמר לובש כמה שיכול
ללבוש, ha amar lovesh kama sheyachol lilvosh, you put on as many
clothes as possible. ועוטף כמה שיכול לעטוף ve'otef kama sheyachol laatof and
you put like headwraps as much as possible if you have to
transport it in this trick way of wearing it. דתנן, detnan, now
this is not about being out of the city, this is about
a fire. ומשם מוציא כל כלי תשמישו. umesham motzi kol klei tashmisho.
It talks about taking stuff from your house that's on fire into
the yard, and says you can take there all of the all
of the things you use. ולובש כל מה שיכול ללבוש velovesh kol
ma sheyachol lilvosh and you can again, it's a problem of carrying
here because the yard didn't have an עירוב eruv or whatever. And
so you can wear out anything that you can wear on your
body. ועוטף כל מה שיכול לעטוף. ve'otef kol ma sheyachol laatof. Okay,
and you can put on your head anything you put on your
head. So you see that you can do it for many, many
items, not just for one. Okay, now so that's against seems to
be against our משנה. mishna. But first, you called it Reb Meir.
Let's establish why you think this is Rabbi Meir. והא סתמא, veha
stama, that סתם משנה stam mishna over there, ממאי דרבי מאיר היא,
mimai deRabbi Meir hee, who told you it was Rabbi Meir? דתניא
עלה detanya ala wow, so you can't say סתם משנה stam mishna
is Rabbi Meir because we also have a סתם משנה. stam mishna.
דתניא עלה detanya ala לובש ומוציא ופושט lovesh umotzi ufoshet because we
have a ברייתא braita that names Rabbi Meir. It says לובש ומוציא
ופושט, lovesh umotzi ufoshet, you wear, bring it out, and then take
the clothes off. ולובש ומוציא ופושט. velovesh umotzi ufoshet. Go back in,
put as much on as possible, come out, take it off, do
it again.
אפילו כל היום כולו afilu kol hayom kulo דברי רבי מאיר. divrei
Rabbi Meir. That's what Meir's saying. Now, it didn't say explicitly in
that ברייתא braita Sabbath and fire, exactly, explicitly in that ברייתא braita
as many clothes as possible, but that is the sense that this
is the position of Rabbi Meir who is giving you a lot
of latitude. So is our משנה mishna that only allows one pair
of תפילין tefillin essentially, and another way of saying it is the
debate of the תנא קמא tana kamma and רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
who allows two pairs, is that tied into this debate about wearing
a lot of clothes? And obviously you could see that the issue
about wearing clothes versus wearing multiple pairs of תפילין tefillin could be
a very different type of a debate. So that's what the גמרא
gemara is getting to, it's first framing it, maybe this is just
a question of can you wear an unusual amount that's more than
you normally wear? So the גמרא gemara says, אמר רבא amar Rava
no. אפילו תימא רבי מאיר, afilu tema Rabbi Meir, it could be
consistent with Rabbi Meir, our משנה. mishna. תפילין tefillin could be different.
התם דרך מלבושא כחול שויוה רבנן. hatam derech malbusha kechol shavyua rabanan.
There, as long as you're wearing it, you know, then it's like
a weekday, meaning not literally like a weekday, but you know, as
long as you're wearing it, it's fine. והכא דרך מלבושא כחול שויוה
רבנן. vehacha derech malbusha kechol shavyua rabanan. Here
we... I'm sorry, I misread that. התם דבחול כמה דבעי לביש, hatam
devachol kama debaei lavish, there when you wear it we consider it
like as would it be normal to wear it during the weekday.
And here if you're wearing it, it's a question about is it
a normal way to wear it during the weekday. התם דבחול כמה
דבעי לביש, hatam devachol kama debaei lavish,
לעניין הצלה נמי שרו ליה רבנן. le'inyan hatzala nami sharu lei rabanan.
During a weekday, you know, a lot of people have very interesting
fashion senses. So if you're the type of person that likes wearing
ten layers of clothing, or three ties, that
would be a little weirder. Anyway, you can do whatever the heck
you want. So therefore, even though it's completely bizarre, it's considered according
to Rabbi Meir legitimate to wear multiple layers of clothing because that
would be within acceptable parameters even during a weekday. You know, you
might be weird but it would be considered acceptable. הכא דבחול נמי
זוג אחד אין טפי לא. hacha devachol nami zug echad in tfi
lo. And here there's a halakhic problem. Wearing more than one pair
of תפילין tefillin is not halakhically acceptable. I thought you said at
one time. And therefore we will we'll discuss it. But let's work
with that assumption and therefore it's not a question of how many
numbers. Oh, it's unusual to wear a lot of תפילין, tefillin, unusual
to wear a lot of clothes. It's that you're not allowed to
wear more than one pair of תפילין. tefillin. And therefore you cannot
do it. So therefore, הכא דבחול נמי זוג אחד אין טפי לא,
hacha devachol nami zug echad in tfi lo, לעניין הצלה נמי זוג
אחד אין טפי לא. le'inyan hatzala nami zug echad in tfi lo.
Here too, there can only be one pair. Now, so the basic
point is this is not just about wearing a lot, okay? It's
about specifically תפילין tefillin and תפילין tefillin you're supposed to wear one,
not two, because more than one at one time is a בל
תוסף bal tosif problem. Now, Michael maybe knows people, I don't know,
normally those that are מקפיד makpid for רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam תפילין
tefillin take off their רש"י Rashi and put on their רבנו תם.
Rabbeinu Tam. There are actually some people that do wear two pairs
of תפילין. tefillin. And we will get to that, but normally on
the face of it it's a בל תוסף bal tosif issue, which
is what the גמרא gemara is about to get to, that that's
really going to be how it's going to focus the debate of
the תנא קמא tana kamma and רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, the parameters
of בל תוסף. bal tosif. Can you wear two pairs? And therefore,
א, aleph, not be over on בל תוסף, bal tosif, but it's
not just a question about not being over on בל תוסף, bal
tosif, it's a question of if you can have a scenario where
two pairs are acceptable, then it also is considered normal wearing on
שבת. Shabbat. But when two pairs are not acceptable because of בל
תוסף bal tosif issues, in addition to being a בל תוסף bal
tosif issue, it turns it into a שבת Shabbat issue as well
because it makes it an unacceptable form of clothing. And that's what
the גמרא gemara is saying is why it's different than the issue
of the multiple layers earlier with Rabbi Meir. Yes. Question.
But they're not totally analogous situations anyway because in the one situation
you're given the permission to save your personal possessions presumably for financial
reasons. Right. And the other, you really have an obligation to save
something that has קדושה. kedusha.
Right. That is true. And you could have said that we even
give more allowance here because we're not just being like giving you
an allowance, we're not just sort of being מיקל, meikel, we're actually
demanding that you do this. That's true. I mean... The גמרא Gemara
could have had other bases of distinction, but I think this was
a perfect segue into analyzing the debate of the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma with רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, which as we're going to see
is very much hinges on issues of בל תוסיף. Bal Tosif. But
you're right, distinguishing it from the case of clothing could have been
based on other things as well.
Yes, and there is another layer to it. In other words, I
can wear my coat on שבת, Shabbat, I wear it on חול.
chol. I don't wear my תפילין tefillin on שבת. Shabbat.
So we'll get to that. So let's take a look at the,
now the גמרא, Gemara, this is a perfect, like I said, lead
in to the next discussion.
Okay. רבן גמליאל אומר rabban gamliel omer, שנים שנים. shnayim shnayim. רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says two at a time. So there's two questions.
One is why does רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel say two and the
חכמים Chachamim one? And the other question is if you can do
two, why not do three? Okay, why limit it to two? So
the גמרא Gemara says like this. מאי קסבר? Mai kasavar? What does
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel hold? אי קסבר שבת זמן תפילין הוא. Ei
kasavar Shabbat zman tefillin hu. If he holds that שבת Shabbat is
the time for wearing תפילין tefillin because the question is going to
be, right? It says we know that we don't wear תפילין tefillin
on שבת Shabbat and the issue is that it's like it's תפילין
tefillin is an אות ot and שבת Shabbat is called an אות
ot and the חז"ל Chazal understood somehow that those would be considered
not only unnecessary to have the אות ot of תפילין, tefillin, but
somehow even in conflict with the קדושה kedusha of שבת. Shabbat. But
that's not on the face of it so obvious and a person
could argue that you're חייב chayav in תפילין tefillin on שבת Shabbat
and there is that theoretical position. So that's what the גמרא Gemara
is first going to be exploring. Can you wear תפילין tefillin on
שבת? Shabbat? So let's take a look. מאי קסבר? Mai kasavar? What
does he hold? אי קסבר שבת זמן תפילין הוא. Ei kasavar Shabbat
zman tefillin hu. שבת Shabbat is a time for wearing תפילין. tefillin.
זוג אחד תפילין. zug echad tefillin.
Then it should be one and not two. Because one is normal,
you wear תפילין tefillin on שבת. Shabbat. Two is unacceptable, it's בל
תוסיף, Bal Tosif, it's whatever it is, it's abnormal and that could
be the end of it. ואי קסבר שבת לאו זמן תפילין הוא.
V'ei kasavar Shabbat lav zman tefillin hu. Let's say you hold שבת
Shabbat is not the time of תפילין. tefillin. So now you would
say if שבת Shabbat isn't the time of תפילין, tefillin, how many
should you be able to wear? None? Zero. Right. But ironically if
שבת Shabbat isn't the time of תפילין, tefillin, then you'll look at
what I'm wearing not as a מצוה, mitzvah, not as the תפילין
tefillin of מצוה, mitzvah, but as a nice, you know, as you
know, it's a nice accessory. Okay, it goes good with my, you
know, white shirt, the black תפילין. tefillin. So therefore if שבת Shabbat
is not זמן תפילין, zman tefillin, you can judge, look at the
wearing of it not through the תפילין tefillin lens where the idea
is only one. So if that's the issue that it's לאו זמן
תפילין, lav zman tefillin, ומשום הצלה, umeshum hatzalah,
and because of the sake of saving it, דרך מלבוש שרו ליה
רבנן, derech malbush sharu lei Rabbanan, the Rabbis allowed it as long
as you're wearing it, אפילו טפי נמי, afilu tfei nami, you could
even, you should even be able to do more than two. So
what is this idea of limiting it to two? So the גמרא
Gemara says like this. לעולם קסבר שבת לאו זמן תפילין הוא. Le'olam
kasavar Shabbat lav zman tefillin hu. Okay, really he's of the opinion
that שבת Shabbat is not the time of תפילין. tefillin. So we're
not going to look at it through that lens. וכי שרו רבנן
משום הצלה דרך מלבוש במקום תפילין. V'chi sharu Rabbanan mishum hatzalah derech
malbush bimkom tefillin.
When did the Rabbis allow you to wear it as a way
of saving it? If you put it in the place of תפילין.
tefillin. You can't put your תפילין, tefillin, you know, have multiple pairs
of תפילין, tefillin, so some of them are coming off my head
like this. Okay. So somehow even though we're going to call it,
even though on the one hand we're not looking at it through
the תפילין tefillin lens to say more than one is not acceptable,
we're looking at it enough through the תפילין tefillin lens to say
is this considered wearing it? Right. If I went ahead and I
took my top, you know, took my, I don't know, suit and
I tied it around my leg, we wouldn't say, well, I'm wearing
it outside, right? So there's a certain point where it's not considered
that's, you know, that's the wrong place for this object and it's
not wearing. So that's why he only allows two. Number one is
we're not looking at it as halachic תפילין, tefillin, but we are
looking at it in the context of where תפילין tefillin is normally
worn and more than two is not going to work.
Okay, one minute.
Okay. אי הכי, Ei hachi, says the גמרא, Gemara, I've just got
with it. אי הכי, Ei hachi, says the גמרא, Gemara, זוג אחד
נמי אין תרי לא. zug echad nami in trei lo. One minute,
if it's only where תפילין tefillin is normally worn, then it should
only be one pair because anything else is outside of the space
of תפילין. tefillin. So
אמר רב שמואל בר רב יצחק מקום יש בראש להניח בו שתי
תפילין. Amar Rav Shmuel bar Rav Yitzchak makom yesh barosh lehaniach bo
shtei tefillin. That actually the head has enough space for two תפילין.
tefillin. Now תוספות Tosafot actually says well how big is the תפילין?
tefillin? So there's a very interesting, so first of all it means
back to back, just so you're aware, not side by side, back
to back, as you know well, whatever, just so you're aware. As
you know that the, you know, the תפילין tefillin as the גמרא
Gemara is going to say is sort of like where the, you
know, the top of the head begins to slope down, but it's
above the, above the hairline. So that's not a lot of space.
Okay. So how big is the תפילין? tefillin? So take a look
at תוספות. Tosafot. מקום יש בראש להניח בו שתי תפילין,
Makom
yesh
barosh lehaniach bo shtei tefillin, says תוספות. Tosafot. מסתפק האי ר"י איזה
שיעור יש ברוחב תפילין. Mistapeik hai Ri eizeh shiur yesh berachav tefillin.
How wide is it? Meaning that would go up on the head,
not across the, across the forehead, up on the head. יש עושים
גדולים מחבריהם ויש עושים אותם קטנים ביותר. Yesh osim gedolim mechavereihem v'yesh
osim otam ktanim beyoter. ומדקאמר מקום יש בראש להניח שתי תפילין משמע
דשיעור רחבו שיתמלא מקום השנים. U'midka'amar makom yesh barosh lehaniach shtei tefillin
mashma d'shiur rachvo sheyitmalei makom hashnayim.
It has to be, you know, it's enough that only, you know,
that it's got to be wide. דאמר ר"י דמצא במדרש דשיעורן כב'
אצבעות. D'amar Ri d'matza b'midrash d'shiuran k'vei etzba'ot.
Two fingers is the minimum sort of like width of the תפילין.
tefillin. And he sort of learns it out from the ציץ. Tzitz.
He believes that the ציץ Tzitz actually was in מקום תפילין, makom
tefillin, which is not obvious. The ציץ Tzitz seems to be on
the forehead. But תוספות Tosafot actually believes that the ציץ Tzitz was
in the place of the תפילין tefillin and that we say was
two fingers and then the כהן Kohen had his hat, his, you
know, and therefore there was a two-finger width between them to put
the תפילין. tefillin. So that's how תוספות Tosafot understands that it's a
two-finger, a two-finger width. Okay, back to the גמרא. Gemara. So it
says like this
so therefore two is considered worn in the normal place and acceptable
so the גמרא Gemara says like this הניחא דראש haniha d'rosh that's
the של ראש shel rosh יד מאי איכא למימר yad mai ika
l'meimar how about the של יד shel yad because the גמרא Gemara
at this stage assumes maybe there's only space on the של יד
shel yad on your arm for one תפילין tefillin maybe it's not
again the zone that's acceptable is not big enough for two so
the גמרא Gemara says כדרב הונא k'deRav Huna no that'll work like
Rav Huna דאמר רב הונא d'amar Rav Huna פעמים שאדם בא מן
השדה pe'amim she'adam ba min hasadeh sometimes a person is coming from
the field וחבילתו על ראשו v'havilato al rosho and he has a
bundle not on Shabbos has a bundle on his head and he's
got תפילין tefillin on his head and the bundle is pushing up
against the תפילין tefillin and moving it around and it's not appropriate
so what does he do ומסלקן מראשו u'mesalkan me'rosho he takes them
not the bundle the תפילין tefillin off of his head וקושרן בזרועו
v'koshran bizro'o and ties them onto his arm so you see that
what sometimes during the week you'll wear תפילין tefillin in the wrong
place because presumably if you're taking the של ראש shel rosh off
you're not putting it in the place of the של יד shel
yad you're putting it somewhere else on your arm so you see
that it would be considered normal to wear תפילין tefillin of the
של יד shel yad in a different place
or you're putting
it on your other arm so the well okay but he alright
that's interesting okay so the גמרא Gemara says אימא דאמר רב הונא
eima d'amar Rav Huna one minute אימא דאמר רב הונא eima d'amar
Rav Huna שלא ינהג בהן דרך ביזיון shelo yinhag bahen derech bizayon
one minute that's what Rav Huna says is that that's acceptable as
a way of protecting the תפילין של ראש tefillin shel rosh from
being sort of you know mistreated from being what's a good word
for ביזיון bizayon denigrated
anyway so that's why you can put it on your arm but
ראוי מי אמר ra'uy mi amar he didn't say that that actually
is a place that's considered like normally a fit place for תפילין
tefillin he's just giving you advice how to get out of how
to protect your של ראש shel rosh אלא כי דאמר רב שמואל
בר רב יצחק ela ki d'amar Rav Shmuel bar Rav Yitzchak מקום
יש בראש שראוי להניח בו שתי תפילין makom yesh barosh she'ra'uy l'haniach
bo shtei tefillin the same way we said that the head has
space for two תפילין tefillin הכא נמי יש ביד hacha nami yesh
bayad מקום יש ביד להניח בו שתי תפילין makom yesh bayad l'haniach
bo shtei tefillin
there's a place in the של יד shel yad so basically what
we are saying is that according to רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel don't
look at this as the מצוה mitzvah of תפילין tefillin that would
only allow one it's not time for תפילין tefillin look at it
as a type of an amulet or essentially some type of an
accessory a clothing accessory but the normal place that it goes is
the place that you normally put תפילין tefillin so two is acceptable
more than because those can fit in the place of תפילין tefillin
more than that is not acceptable תנא דבי מנשה tana d'vei Menashe
we taught from the house of Menashe על ידך al yadecha now
we're going to talk a little bit about where the תפילין tefillin
go על ידך al yadecha זו קיבורת zu kibores this is not
the hand the palm but this is actually the biceps בין עיניך
bein einecha between your eyes not again literally between your eyes but
זו קדקד zu kodkod this is actually the top of the head
what's it called this place not the skull but what crown crown
the crown the crown of your head so היכא heicha okay so
היכא אמרי דבי רב ינאי heicha amrei d'vei Rav Yannai היכא heicha
where is this exactly this crown the place of the של ראש
shel rosh אמרי דבי רב ינאי amrei d'vei Rav Yannai מקום שמוחו
של תינוק רופס makom she'mocho shel tinok rofes the soft spot of
a baby's head what's it called soft spot
is that what it's called anyway anyway the place where it's soft
because I think it's like what the plates don't fuse right away
or something anyway that is the place of the של ראש shel
rosh okay now back to the debate of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
and the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma now why again two and one
what's it about so we have said that it's about whether שבת
Shabbos is זמן תפילין zman tefillin or לאו זמן תפילין lav zman
tefillin the גמרא Gemara is going to have a couple of other
permutations
לימא leima says the גמרא Gemara בדרב שמואל בר רב יצחק קמיפלגי
b'deRav Shmuel bar Rav Yitzchak kamifligi maybe they're debating this question about
is there space for one pair or two pairs of תפילין tefillin
they all agree don't you know look at it through the מצוה
mitzvah lens but they're still debating what's an acceptable space to put
it on תנא קמא לית ליה דרב שמואל בר רב יצחק Tanna
Kamma leis lei deRav Shmuel bar Rav Yitzchak Tanna Kamma doesn't hold
that there's space for two there's only space for one ורבן גמליאל
אית ליה דרב שמואל בר רב יצחק v'Rabban Gamliel is lei deRav
Shmuel bar Rav Yitzchak and Rabban Gamliel holds of it so maybe
that's what the debate is גמרא Gemara says לא lo no דכולי
עלמא אית להו דרב שמואל בר רב יצחק de'kulei alma is lehu
deRav Shmuel bar Rav Yitzchak everybody would hold of that והכא בשבת
זמן תפילין קמיפלגי v'hacha b'Shabbos zman tefillin kamifligi like we said before
they're arguing whether שבת Shabbos is the time of תפילין tefillin דתנא
קמא סבר שבת זמן תפילין הוא d'Tanna Kamma savar Shabbos zman tefillin
hu ורבן גמליאל סבר שבת לאו זמן תפילין הוא v'Rabban Gamliel savar
Shabbos lav zman tefillin hu now again the irony is when שבת
Shabbos is לאו זמן תפילין lav zman tefillin it allows you to
wear more now why until now what I've said I've simplified it
a little bit and until now what I've said is the reason
if it's לאו זמן תפילין lav zman tefillin it's more is that
then you don't look at it as a מצוה mitzvah and you're
saying oh only one is acceptable you look at it through a
different lens as a type of an accessory a clothing accessory and
you say oh okay so one two whatever תוספות Tosfos however makes
another point which ties into the next part of the גמרא Gemara
which we'll continue with tomorrow which is תוספות Tosfos says no
it is easier to be עובר over on בל תוסיף bal tosif
when it's the זמן zman of a מצוה mitzvah after the time
of a because the whole idea rabbinic idea of בל תוסיף bal
tosif is you're doing a מצוה mitzvah and you're expanding it once
it's the time of the it's not the time of the מצוה
mitzvah if I were today to take a לולב ואתרוג lulav v'esrog
and shake it and say אנא ה' הושיעה נא ana Hashem hoshia
na would I be עובר over on בל תוסיף bal tosif probably
not I'd be doing something stupid but I'm not expanding a מצוה
mitzvah because I haven't started with a מצוה mitzvah okay so therefore
it's easier to be עובר over on בל תוסיף bal tosif when
it's the time of תפילין tefillin so that's the way תוספות Tosfos
explains he says if שבת Shabbos is זמן תפילין zman tefillin you're
going to only be limited to one. As soon as you do
two, because this is the time of תפילין, tefillin, it's בל תוסיף.
bal tosif. And then not only are you transgressing בל תוסיף, bal
tosif, presumably also then it would be carrying, because then that would
define the other one as completely unacceptable and extra. Whereas if שבת
Shabbos is לאו זמן תפילין, lav zman tefillin, there's no בל תוסיף
bal tosif discussion, and therefore, the only discussion is does it look
normal to wear one, two, however many it looks normal to wear.
So we'll pick up with that tomorrow, and see how בל תוסיף
bal tosif becomes an important part of this debate and of determining
whether you can wear more than one pair of תפילין tefillin or
not. Okay.